Hey guys, Shan this said welcome back to
the channel and today in spring boot we
are going to cover actuator. So let's
start without wasting any time. Actuator
provide production ready endpoints to
monitor and manage the spring boot
application. Okay, how let's say that
whatever the project you have all you
need to add is your actuator dependency.
Okay, if you are creating a fresh
project just add this dependency also.
Internally it brings this spring - booty
starter - actuator to your pom.xml.
Okay. And if you already have the
project setup just add this dependency.
Okay. Once the dependency is set now if
you see the application.properties
there are two major property. Okay. So
this one is al optional. First one is
optional. management.endpoints.base
dot base path. Okay, so base path. So I
use /manage.
I told you it's optional. If I don't use
it, the base path would be /actuator.
Okay. So activator provide
production ready endpoints. There are so
many endpoints. So you can say that this
is the base path. So there would be like
slash after that there would be metric
name. There are so many. But base is
this /actuator/metric
name. Okay. But since I have overrided
it because I don't want to use
/actuator, I want my personalized. So I
use /manage.
Okay. But this is optional.
Another property is also you can say
that optional
management.endpoints.exposure.incclude.
So currently I have put a star means all
the matrices all the matress endpoints
are exposed.
Okay. If
I told you that it's an optional if it
is not added if this property is not
added only health
and info these two endpoints are
visible. Okay you would be able to
invoke only these two endpoints others
are not. So if you want only selected
then you can use comma separated here
like health comma info endpoint comma
metrics endpoint comma loggers endpoint
likewise but for testing purpose we want
to enable all the endpoints so I put a
star here
okay but if you this is also an optional
if you don't add it only these two
endpoints you would be able to hit okay
so that's all we have added the
dependency in application.properties
properties we have added and generally
both are optional and we are just
starting our application and our
application is started now if you see
that
I am hitting this endpoint /manage/halth
so this is the base one instead of /
activator I have changed it to /manage
in application.property property and
this is /halth. Now it give me this
it means that my server is up and
running. Okay. So it give me certain in
data information.
Similarly there is another endpoint
/metric. If I invoked it like /manage
this is my base /metric. Okay. What it
return? it return me all the end points
which are currently available within
this matrix. Okay. So let's say that I
pick one of this endpoint.
So I have to call like slash manage this
is the base. Okay. Slashmatrix because
we are going to use this one and one we
are going to use one of the matrix of
which are present inside this /matrix
and we are using this one
executor.pool.core.
So /manage/metric/executor.pool.core.
So it returns me like what all the
threadpool executors are present and
what's the thread pool size.
Okay. So likewise you see that there are
lot more matrices available for JVM for
your CPU process for your server. Okay.
for your thread pool executor. You can
get lot more information about your
system.
Okay.
So
let's see some useful inbuilt actuator
endpoint. So these are also an inbuilt
only but this is just to show the demo
like okay how you can add actuator
within your project. Very simple. All
you need is your dependency. You have to
enable or expose the endpoints which you
have to use. This is optional. If you
don't use it, you have to use /actuator
as a base path. If you want, you can
give some meaningful name like /manage.
Okay. And you are able to hit the end
points.
So there are so many endpoints like
/halth.
Now let's
further deep into this because this is
very important one.
So by default it provide the health
status of our application whether it's
up down out of service unknown. Okay
currently our app is up and running so
that's why it is giving up.
So here if you see that we can even
extend to add additional check. So apart
from so let's say that my requirement is
that hey okay my application is up and
running my Tomcat is up and running but
I also want to check like hey what about
my DB is it up and running or not what
about the cache what about the my
message broker so once if all of this
are up then only I want to make my
system up if any of them is down it
should be down okay so that also you can
extend ended. Okay. So very simple in
this one let's say that I am adding DB
functionality into the health itself.
Okay. So this is something that I am
writing a class database health
indicator. This is the class name which
I have given. You can give any name. All
you have to do is you have to implement
health indicator. This health indicator
interface is for this slash endpoint /
health endpoint. Okay. So we have to
provide an implementation for this
health method.
So since it is database so you can have
your custom logic here to check whether
the DB is up or not. So here for now I
am just returning true. But in the
production we can simulate like by
checking whether that I'm able to query
DB or not. Okay. So for now let's say I
am returning true that yes my DB is up.
So if it DB is up I am making health dot
up. Okay for the DB. So for each one
there is a health for each one there is
a health. So I'm making its health up.
Okay.
And also I have added the message like
DB available. If it is not available I
am making the health down and with
message like DB not available. Similarly
for cache I am doing another class cache
health indicator which implements health
indicator implemented the health method.
Check the cache status. And now here if
you notice that I specifically made it
false. Okay, just for testing purpose.
Now if the cache is up, I can make cache
health. So it health is up or down
whatever
we are doing. So for now it is false. So
it would be health dot down with message
like cache not available.
Okay. So now if you hit this
/manage/help
okay you will see that hey got a status
down hey why why only this one where is
this message DB available or cache not
available and why down so see
the above status one is aggregated one
aggregated one and inside this it has
multiple so where we have DB we have
cache. Okay. So when all are up, when
everything is up, then only the above
status is up. If any one of the sub
component or submetric you can say that
is down, the above one is down also.
Okay. So but you can say that okay that
is understood but where is the
information? I'm not able to see my DB
and this cache which I have added. Okay.
I know that this is down because for the
cash one I have specifically made false
and for cash it is down. So that's why
my overall aggregated is down also. But
where is the information?
See by default health only show this
much above status. But if you want a
complete details also we have to add
this management.point Endpoint dot
health
show hyphen details equals to always. By
default it's never. Okay. Once you add
this application.properties and hit it
again. Okay. Now here if you see the
details are added. Cache details. We
make it the status down specifically.
And this is the info cache not
available. For database it's up and
detail is DB available. And since once
subservice is down, the overall status
is down.
Okay.
Similarly, we have so many matrices,
right? We have uh /metric endpoint and
we have already seen that when you
invoke this one, it gives you a list of
all the matrices which are available
within this. And we can access
particular
matress like this /matrix/ particular
matrix within this. Okay. So there are
so many available inside this matrices
like
JVM do.memory dot use.
How much memory currently used by the
JVM. So you can get that information.
Okay. JVM domemory domax. What is the
maximum memory JVM can use? So how you
can use this that slashmanage
slashmatrix
slashmatrix slash right because these
are all the matrices are present within
this endpoint okay so this I want to use
this so jvm dot memory dot use so it
will give you this info
similar you can get garbage collection
matrices like JVMGc
okay so you can get multiple information
that okay total number of GC events
occur how many time GC has run total
time spent and what is the longest
single GC pause observe okay so you can
get all this information
similarly you can get information
regarding your thread your system uh
usage
uh your request https server request if
you use this you can get what is the
total number of HTTP requests you have
received total time spent handling all
all the requests long longest time taken
to handle single request. All this
information you can get. Okay. So you
can play different uh with this
different endpoints you will get better
information depending upon your need
your company what matrix you are
interested in. Okay. So there are more
like thread dum heap dum. So those
information are also available. So
another API is like /manage
slash thread dump.
Okay. So it helps you to diagnose
deadlock or thread leaks. Which thread
are active, blocked, waiting. Okay. Even
the stack trace what code is executing
by which thread thread name and
everything. So this is output you will
get. Hey this is the thread currently.
It is the stack trace. Currently it is
running this code. it is currently like
waiting or blocked or what is the state
runnable different thread. So all this
information you will get whatever you
want. Okay. So this is the official
documentation.
Okay. Um I will put into the description
section also you can use it. It has a
list of all the endpoints and based on
your company needs and the metrics which
you are interested in you can use that.
Okay. So you have heapd mappings beans
what are beans in your uh spring
application is there shutdown okay
loggers so many thing okay now only
thing specifically I want to mention
that this shutdown and heapdom even
though we have put a star right you
remember exposed all the end points
here exposed all the end point a are
even after that also you won't be able
to hit /shutdown and /hipdom like
slashmanage
slash shutdown and slashmanage slash
heap dump you won't be able to hit it
why because they are very critical
endpoints when you invoke shutdown it
will stop your application when you call
the heap dump right it will expose
sensitive ative information like some
token, password etc. So spring boot want
you to take additional
you can say that uh measure that hey yes
you are totally accepted the risk
involved by exposing then these
endpoints. So for this you have to
specifically me uh mention like this in
the property management.point.hipdump
Heap dump dot access unrestricted.
Currently it's restricted. Similarly for
shutdown also management.point dot
shutdown do.ac unrestricted. After that
only you would be able to access this.
Even though you have mentioned start you
have to unrestricted manually. It is
just way of saying that springboard
would saying hey you have accepted the
risk involved.
Okay. So you can say that with great
power actuator provide you great power
the responsibility great responsibility
also comes
okay security very important part here
in that is all these endpoints are
generally public okay so like /hel
/info/matrix
slash whatever the pool jvm these are
all public anybody can invoke it if they
know your URL and port number. Okay. And
these can expose some critical info
about your system. You don't want
anybody to be get uh call this endpoint.
So you have to add security to this
endpoint. So we have already covered
spring security in depth. Kindly check
it out. All we can do is that you have
in the dependency you have to add the
spring security. Okay. We have already
covered if you have already covered
spring security you might already know
this thing very simple part. So you need
a spring security dependency
and in the security config we have again
I'm saying you if you haven't seen the
spring security video you might be
seeing this as uh out of the context
like what is going on but that's what I
mentioned like kindly check it out
spring security where we have discussed
everything this in depth okay so there
we have a filter chain so here I have
put that okay only the health and info
you can permit everything. Okay. But for
any other request you need to
authenticate. So even if you don't want
to this you can just simply say any
request authenticated. Okay. You can
choose any authentication JWT for here I
am just using basic authentication for
testing purpose. Okay. And in
application.properties
you can provide username password. Again
this is just for testing basic
authentication. Okay. For more in depth
like how security works you can check it
out here.
So just wanted to highlight that you can
secure these endpoints like any request
you have to authenticate or you can add
more like hey request
matcher
like any endpoint start with uh
slashmanage
or slash activator say
star any endpoint start with this should
has role
Let's say admin,
you can add this. We have already seen
this before how we can do that. But I'm
saying that you can reuse those to
manage your actuator endpoints that they
have some specific roles and they should
be properly authenticated before anybody
can use it. Okay.
So let's say that if I try to use it /
env without providing the authentication
it will say unauthorized and after
providing username and password it able
it show me the data okay so before
proceeding further if you haven't seen
the spring security kindly check it out
because uh I'm not covering here because
that would be duplicate and it's not a
small topic there are total overall nine
parts in this on. So spring security is
a very big topic. So kindly check it out
and this all these things would be
clear. So just at here my intention is
to just tell that always make sure that
in spring security you have a
specifically checking that all the
actuator endpoints has a specific role
checks for authorization and it should
be authenticated also.
This is very important
custom actuator endpoints. Okay. So like
we have so many endpoint like slash
activuator or let's say that we have
changed it to slashmanage right. We can
add our own custom endpoint here also.
How
with this annotation add the rate
endpoint.
Okay. So over the class you just need to
annotate at the rate endpoint id equals
to whatever the name you will give. So
see this example. So I have written one
class like my custom stats endpoint any
name which you can give and this is a
bean. So you have to put add the red
component. Now all I have added is add
the red endpoint
id equals to this is the endpoint I have
added my custom stats. So this will
become /actuator slash or slashmanage
slash
this one my custom stats. So this is the
new endpoint actuator endpoint I have
added. Now now within this class
we can either have read operation it's
equivalent to get we can have write
operation equivalent to post and we can
have delete operation equivalent to
delete.
Okay within this class. So now let's say
that within this class I have exposed
the endpoint I am adding read operation
two read operation.
So one is I am adding a method public
string read all and I'm just returning
hello spring boot. Okay. So now I have
annotated with add the rate read
operation. So this is a get. So if you
hit a get request
slash activuator
or slashmanage whatever slash this
endpoint my custom stats that's all. And
this is a get call. So which method it
will invoke? It will invoke this method.
Okay. So it will return hello spring
boot.
Similarly I have added another method
add annotated with add the read
operation. But here if you see that I
have added some selectors. Selector is
more like after this one we can provide
certain you can say that placeholder for
that for name I can have let's say shan
share
message hello
okay so you can say that after this your
end point after this your end point
these are selectors selector one
selector two selector three which are in
sequence and it should be matched with
it in sequence
Okay. So now I have let's say /actuator
slash my custom strat slash I have put
shriange. So this get mapped to this
one. Hello. This get mapped to this one.
Okay. So two selectors. So it will pick
a method and it's a get. So it pick a
read operation method and has two
actuator uh two selectors. So this
method will get invoked.
And yes, one more thing we have to add
before running is so this is the custom
endpoint we have to expose it also.
Okay. So you you if you are using
selected one health comma info comma you
have to provide here also otherwise you
can just simply put a star it will
automatically get exposed. Okay. Now if
I just hit /manage uh because I have
override /actuator so I'm using /manage
slash my custom stat so this is a get
call and no selector so this method will
get invoked hello spring boot
now I am calling /manage/
my custom endpoint now this is selector
one selector two so it will pick one get
so this is get call right it will pick
some get read operation method which has
two selector matching it name message is
both are string so it will get invoked.
Okay. Similarly we have write operation
and delete operation. Okay. So this is
post this is delete.
Okay. So
return type can be anything. It return
type at anywhere you can have either
string primitive pojo whatever you want
to return. Okay. So write operation is
also no difference in that. Delete
operation no difference in that. You can
even have selectors also like this I'm
using. So I have a refresh method
annotated with write. So any endpoint
which is invoking post slashmanage or
activator slash my custom stats. So this
is a post no selectors. So it will see
that which method with right operation
matches it. So this will get matched and
this code will get executed.
Similarly, if it is a delete http method
and /manage slash my custom stat and the
selector is like key my key. So it will
see that okay delete. So it will look
for all the method which are annotated
with delete and then it will try to
match the selector. So one selector only
which is string matched this will get
executed.
Okay.
And also very important that spring boot
considered this write and delete
operation very critical. Okay. So it
requires authentication for that one. If
you have writing a custom endpoint and
you are using write operation and delete
operation right then springboard say
that hey these are critical means it is
changing something post and delete okay
so it is specifically want that you
should have authentication for it so you
can just simply add the same security
filter any request you want it to be
authenticated that's all okay for if you
are just using get read operation even
though you are not adding security you
would be able to hit properly. Okay. But
if you are using write and delete
operation specifically you have to make
sure that these endpoints actuator
endpoints
or specifically let's say this where the
write and delete operations are present
on this endpoint at least this should be
authenticated.
Okay. And again you have to make sure
that you include this
okay or expose this or use star okay and
uh if you see that now if you're calling
post my custom stat you have to provide
username password because it has to be
authenticated it got invoked similarly
delete
this endpoint and one selector so it
will match the method you have to
provide username password because we are
authenticating here basic Basic
authentication.
Okay.
So,
reset done. It work.
Okay. Very important part. This is very
important. Adding a new custom endpoint
actuator endpoint is very important
because this is used by a lot
frameworks. Let's say that even the
refresh
scope
okay in the centralized configuration
that also uses it. We will see that
later but I'm just want to say that lot
of spring frameworks uses this
functionality that they expose an
endpoints and if we call them it do
something okay and uh those endpoints
are supported through this actuator
endpoints custom endpoints.
Now one more important thing is hey I
got it actuator help us to provide the
metrics
and these metric we can push to
monitoring platform you can you know
that there are so many monitoring
platform one of the very popular is data
dog another is prometheus cloudatch I
think cloudatch is from Amazon okay so
there are so many monitoring platforms
available so we can push this data to
this monitoring platform also. So how
see this might not be needed but this is
you can say that in the companies they
are using it. Okay. So to understand the
actuator you can say that you can skip
it but I would say that within a company
definitely you might be using some
monitoring platform for your
application. there you will see that
internally how it actually your
application is putting the data into
your monitoring platform. So now let's
say in the data doc I'm using data talk
and currently I took a free trial of it.
Now in this one I goes to my this
profile and here if you see that there
is something called API keys within the
API keys I created a new key and copied
it.
Now in the application.properties
I just added this management dot data
dog dot matrix dot export dot API key
and I added this API key. Okay. So this
is since this is a testing profile.
Okay. So that's why I'm adding it here.
But it's never recommended to add a key
like this in the application.properties.
Either add it into environment variable.
But this is a profile just for testing.
Okay. So you can uh add key I added the
key like this here. Okay.
Another thing is you have to enable the
export true means that you are allowing
the spring boot to push the data to the
data do. Okay. And another is that in
which frequency spring boot has to push
the data. So I put 5 second means every
5 second it will push the metric to the
data dog
and yes you need to add the dependency
also. So I added the dependency
micrometer - registry data dog. So this
dependency I have added okay and I added
this application.properties properties
and in the data doc profile you have
created the key use that key here
very simple okay now all the metrics of
a spring boot actuator now automatically
push to the data dog if you open a data
dog and here you'll see metrics
okay so here in the same one you will
see the metrics right so if you click
the metric you will see summary explore
volume and within a summary you will see
a list of matrices. So I open just one
matrix like http.server
request count if I open it you able to
see certain graphs now. So every time I
invoke my application it's like a
request I making a request. So it is
like a count graph is
that those datas get published to data
dog and this you will get certain graphs
to visualize and monitor.
Okay. So if you check out this summary
you will see like so many hundred of uh
matrices. You can choose the matric
which you want to monitor and you can
see your application health.
Okay. Try it out. It's very interesting
like and lot of learning. Okay. But if
you still have any doubt let me know. We
can discuss further. Okay guys. Thank
you. Bye.